Mss.B.C55
American Philosophical Society
Hans Thacher Clarke Papers
Circa 1903-1973
Mss.B.C55
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet 3,500 items
Circa 3500 items (3 linear ft.). From Finding Aid: 7 boxes & 12 notebooks, 5,000 items (1912-1972)
This collection contains correspondence, reports, notes, and notebooks. Clarke's participation in various organizations is documented, including the American Philosophical Society, American Chemical Society, American Otological Society, and the American Society of Biological Chemists. His chemistry research is detailed in thirteen notebooks, 1903-1971 (the 1903 volume is on photographic chemistry and processes). There is also one volume on the clarinet, for Clarke was an expert clarinetist. The personal and family correspondence is principally with Mrs. Dorothy Clarke Middleton and Mrs. Agnes Helfreich Clarke.
Clarke, Agnes Helfreich
Clarke, Hans Thacher, 1887-1972
Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978
Du Vigneaud, Vincent, 1901-1978
Emerson, Alfred E., (Alfred Edwards), 1896-1976
Fruton, Joseph S., (Joseph Stewart), 1912-
Gies, William John, 1872-1956
Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975
Long, Esmond R., (Esmond Ray), 1890-
Luck, James Murray, 1899-
Middleton, Dorothy Clarke
Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975
Planck, Erwin
Shockley, William, 1910-
Smiles, Samuel, 1877-1953
Sperry, Warren Myron, 1900-
Stewart, Alfred W., (Alfred Walter), b. 1880
Taylor, Geoffrey Ingram, Sir, 1886-1975
Tuve, Merle Antony, 1901-1982
Box 1-6
Scope and Contents note
D. ca. 5000 items. Various sizes. Presented by Mrs. Clarke; June 7, 1973.
Much of the collection concerns Clarke's family life and his involvement with the arts. Clarke, an expert carinetist, was frequently asked to give concerts as local halls (see notebook 11).
Seven files of correspondence from unknown individuals are largely concerned with personal affairs.
Of Clarke's correspondence, the most interesting exchanges are contained in letter from A.W. Stewart (Box 7), Sirl Julian Huxley (Box 4, 17 items, 1958-1972), Sir Geoffrey Taylor (Box 7, c.30 items, 1955-1972), J. Murray Luck (Box 5, 9 letters, 1956-65), Samuel Smiles (Box 7, c.15 items, 1926-34), and members of his family, Mrs. Agnes Helfreich (c.40 items) and Mrs. Dora Middleton (c.70 items).
In addition to correspondence, the collection contains Clarke's chemical laboratory notebooks dated from 1928 to 1971 and some printed material, such as the testimony of Philip handler tot he Subcommittee of Science, Research and Development in the U.S. House of Representatives in 1971. Some routine memo materials, such as those accompanying chemicals sent to Stephen Nagy's M.I.T. analysis laboratory from 1957 to 1964 (Box 5, 35 items) is scatter through the collection. [composed by Margaret Miller, Archives Coordinator, Survey of Souces for the History of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology].
Box 2 contains 4 files, c. 200 items, 1957-1964 relating to the Journal of Biochemical Preparations. List of Editorial board members of Advisory Boards, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1961, 1964. Some drafts of chemical procedures to be included in several of the volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
Hans Thacher Clarke studied chemistry at University College, London (1896-1905), worked for the Eastman Kodak Co. in Rochester (1914-1928), and was a professor of biological chemistry at the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University (1928-1956). Among other researches, he was involved in the production of penicillin in the U.S.
Hans Thacher Clarke (1887-1972) was born in Harrow, England. From 1896-1905, he attended University College London School, and went on to enter the University as a student of chemistry. There he studied under William Ramsey, J. N. Collie and Samuel Smiles. He also attended courses in physiological chemistry taught by R.H. A Plimmer and physiology with E. H. Starling, but found these studies boring at the time. After receiving his B.Sc. in 1908, Clarke continued to do research at University College under the direction of Smilesand A.W. Stewart. In 1911, he was awarded an 1851 Exhibition Scholarship which he used to spend three semesters with Emil Fischer in Berlin and one semester with A.W. Stewart at Queen's College, Belfast. On his return he was granted the D.Sc. from London University in 1913.
Clarke's father had long been associated with Eastman Kodak Company as European representative. George Eastman occasionally consulted Hans on chemical matter and, at the beginning of World War I, when the company was forced to produce photographic chemicals which they had previously imported from Germany, they turned to Hans for help. Clarke moved to Rochester, N.Y. in 1914 only to discover that he was the sole organic chemist there! The correspondence retained from these years consists largely of requests for chemicals, arrangements for visits, and reports of Clarke's consultancy work which involved scanning the chemical literature (a task which continued to occupy him for two days a week until 1969!) [Box 3, 3 files, c.60 items, 191-1963]
At the suggestion of his friend Henry D. Dakin, Clarke accepted a position offered him as Professor of Biological Chemisty at Columbia's College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1928. When he first took on the post he received much advice from his friend and mentor, A.W. Stewart on how to start one's own academic department (Box 7, c. 20 items, 1926-1935). While at Columbia, Clarke took a personal interest in graduate students, of whom he demanded rigorous qualifications prior to admission (a list of the PhD.s granted from 1913 to 1957, with their positions as of 1955, is in Box 2, "Biochemistry at Columbia"). As time went on, Clarke found less and less time to devote to his own research. Other responsibilities interrupted his work, including the 1953 memorial lectures for his friend Henry Dankin, and subsequent arrangements for this event at Adelphi College every year to 1965 (Box 1, Adelphia Colege, 3 files, 1957-1965).
In 1956, Clarke retired from Columbia, but continued his research and some lecturing and conducting student seminars at the Biochemical Laboratories of the Graduate School of Yale University, to which he had been invited by Joseph Fruton. This arrangement was disrupted when the Medical School needed the space Clarke was occupying in the laboratory to accommodate newly appointed members of its staff in 1964 (Box 5, Dean Vernon W. Lippard). Clarke was able to continue his research at the Children's Cancer Research Foundation Center in Boston until 1970, when ill health forced him to retire.
One of the jobs Clarke valued most was his position, in 1951-1952, as Science Attache to the American Embassy in London. His post permitted him to work closely with Sir Robert Robinson, with whom he had edited a major book on research in penicillin in 1949, after prior government service as Assistant Director of the Office of Scientific Research and Development in 1944 placed him in charge of coordinating penicillin production in the U.S. (Box 4, Paul D. Foote, and Box 6, 1959-1960, concern a controversy on patenting of production methods in U.K. and U.S. which casts light on Clarke's role in the penicillin production effort).
Clarke's activities int he NAS, including records of his receipt of the King's medal in 1948 and vitae of nominees from 1942 to 1971 have been retained (Box 6). His activity as chairman of the Rochester section of the American Chemical Society (1921), of the New York section (1946) and of the Organic Chemisty Division (1924-25) as well as his work on the Committee on Professional Training, and the Garvin Award Committee, are well documented (Box 1, 6 files). Clarke was also the president of teh American Society of Biological Chemists in 1947, but the collection contains very little of interest in this regard (Box 2, 5 files, 50 items, c. 1942-1963).
Clarke's activity on grants allocation committees is well documented. As a member of teh Otological Society he served on a grants committee from 1956-1962 (Box 1, 9 files). As Chairman of the Merck Fellowship Board of the National Academy of Sciences in 1957, Clarke retained such interesting correspondence as a letter from Warren Weaver to A.N. Richards recommending the use of the Merck money for two or three research professorships at $15,000 p.a. rather than only for post-doctoral research, and a letter from Kenneth B. Raper at Wisconsin approving of this proposal which was passed on to the Merck Board in March 1957 (Box 5).
Clarke was in much demand for his talents as a lucid writer and was called on to serve as editor or referee throughout his career. He served on the editorial board of Organic Synthesis from 1921 to 1932 (Box 6, 3 files), of the Journal of Biological Chemistry from 1937 to 1951, and as associate editor of the Journal of the American Chemical Society from 1928 to 1938 (JBC, Box 4, 8 files up to 1960, also, Box 3, Clarke's 50th Anniversary article on the Journal).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift from Mrs. Hans Clarke and accessioned, 06/07/1973.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
The appointment of Hans Thacher Clarke as chairman of the biochemistry department of Columbia's College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1928 signaled a disciplinary shift away from a clinical orientation toward a biochemistry firmly rooted in organic and physical chemistry. In urging him to assume the chairmanship, James Conant wrote to Clarke, "Here is a Medical Group that at last have seen the light and want a straight organic chemist to run the show" (May 23, 1928).
Clarke's background in academic and industrial organic chemistry had had little connection to medical problems. A protege of William Ramsay at University College in London, and later a student of Emil Fischer, Clarke specialized in the synthesis of proteins. During World War I and until his move to Columbia, Clarke engaged in research and development of photographic chemicals at Eastman Kodak, retaining a consultantship with Kodak until 1969. During these years Clarke acquired a reputation among organic chemists as a superb organizer of research.
His administrative skills and ability to recognize talent contributed to the growth of Columbia's biochemistry department, which by the 1940s had become one of the largest and most influential in the United States.
During the 1930s, Clarke opened his laboratory to refugee biochemists, among them E. Brand, Erwin Chargaff, Z. Dische, K. Meyer, D. Nachmansohn, R. Schoenheimer, and Heinrich Waelsch. Unfortunately, the correspondence does not reflect the scope of these activities.
Adams, Roger, 1889-1971 Correspondence (3 items) 1947-1968 English
American Chemical Society ( Reflects Clarke's broad range of professional activities.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1956-1966 English
American Society of Biological Chemists ( Reflects Clarke's broad range of professional activities.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1942-1963 English
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975 ( Located within Merck Fellowships #1.) Correspondence (2 items) 1957 English
Chargaff, Erwin, 1905-2002 ( Contains material reflecting Clarke's influence and popularity among his students and colleagues.) Correspondence (1 item) 1958 English
Clarke, Hans Thacher, 1887-1972. Biochemistry at Columbia ( Includes a list of doctorates granted in biochemistry at Columbia University from 1913 to 1957, with the positions of the graduates in 1955.) Manuscripts (6 items) 1955-1957 English
Clarke, Hans Thacher, 1887-1972. Laborartory Notebooks ( Clarke's chemistry research is detailed in thirteen notebooks. The 1903 volume is on photographic chemistry and processes.) Notebooks (13 volumes) 1903-1971 English
Du Vigneaud, Vincent, 1901-1978 ( Describes Du Vigneaud's graduate student days at the University of Rochester.) Correspondence (7 items) 1955-1972 English
Eastman Kodak Company ( Covers the period of Clarke's research and development of photographic chemicals at Eastman Kodak, and his later consultancy with the company. During these years Clarke acquired a reputation among organic chemists as a superb organizer of research.) Correspondence (3 folders (approximately 60 items)) 1912-1963 English
Fruton, Joseph S. (Joseph Stewart), 1912-2007 Correspondence (7 items) 1955-1972 English
Gies, William John, 1872-1956 ( Letters related to biographical material on Gies.) Correspondence (6 items) 1956 English
Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975 Correspondence (17 items) 1958-1972 English
Lorente de No, Rafael ( No informs Clarke of the death of Heinrich Waelsch, a former refugee bichemist for whom Clarke opened his laboratory.) Correspondence (1 item) 1966 English
Luck, James Murray, 1899-1993 Correspondence (9 items) 1956-1965 English
Merck Fellowship Board ( Regarding Clarke's chairmanship.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1956-1959 English
Nachmansohn, David, 1899-1983 ( Correspondence with a former refugee bichemist for whom Clarke opened his laboratory.) Correspondence (10 items) 1961-1969 English
National Academy of Sciences ( Reflects Clarke's broad range of professional activities.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1942-1963 English
Shockley, William, 1910-1989 Correspondence (2 folders) 1968-1970 English
Smiles, Samuel Correspondence (15 items) 1926-1934 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 Correspondence (4 items) 1956-1960 English
Stewart, Alfred W. (Alfred Walter), 1880-1947 ( Contains materials regarding the development of the new biochemistry department at Columbia University.) Correspondence (Approximately 20 items) 1926-1935 English
Taylor, Geoffrey Ingram, Sir, 1886-1975 Correspondence (Approximately 30 items) 1955-1972 English
Tuve, Merle Antony, 1901-1982 ( Biographical material on Clarke.) Correspondence (4 items) Circa 1964 English
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter), 1883-1971 Correspondence (5 items) 1953-1963 English
American Chemical Society.; American Otological Society.; American Philosophical Society.; American Society of Biological Chemists.; Biochemistry -- United States.; Biochemistry.; Clarinet.; Medicine -- United States.; Penicillin.; Photographic chemistry.
- Papers
  - Abelson, Philip H, 1963-1967
    Scope and Contents note
    22 items, 1963-1967 [Box 1] Abelson write to H.T. Clarke asking Clarke to sugest suthors and subject for leading biochemical articles in Science. List of articles published in the field of biochemistry in Science for the years, 1962, 1966 & 1967.
    General note
    See: See also: Science, in: See also in: American Association for the Advancement of Science
  - Academic Press, Inc.
    1 item. [Box 1] Re. classification of article written by Clarke into subject area.
    See: See also:
  - Adams, Roger, 1947, 1968
    3 items, 1947 & 1968 [Box 1] Personal letters re relatives and friends of bot Clarke and Adams. Reference to candidate to replace Fred Seitz at the NAS.
    See: Conant, James BSee also:
  - Adelphi University # 1, 1953-1965; Aldelphi College Correspondence (15 May, 1953)
    Eddy, Paul Dawson; Williams, Carroll M[ilton]; Stetten, DeWitt, Jr.; Fruton, Joseph S.; Aldelphi College Correspondence (15 May, 1953)
    3 files, c. 200 items, 1953-1965. [Box 1] Copy of H. Dale's first memorial lecture at Adelphia College, "Henry Drysdale Dakin, His Life and Work." Copy of a letter from A.N. Richards of the University of Pennsylvania to President P.D. Eddy of Adelphi College in which Richards informed Eddy of the decision of Merck Co. Inc. to donate $7, 500 to the Adelphi College for the preservation of the H.D. Dakin Memorial Lectures as an annual function. Futher letters re: contribution to the H.D. Dakin Memorial Lectures fund.
    Letters from Clarke advising the Adelphi College how to extend its biochemistry courses to the graduate level and discussion of plans to extend the new chemistry building at Adelphi College.
    Most of the material in these three files deals directly with the Dakin Memorial Lectures.
    See: Clarke, H. T. First Dakin Memorial LectureSee also:
  - Adelphi University # 2
    Eddy, Paul Dawson; Sheehan, John Clark; Wald, George; Eickelberg, W. Warren B.; Clark, Willaim Mansfield.
  - Adelphi University # 3
    Eddy, Paul Dawson; Clark, William M.; Eickelberg, W. Warren B.; Vogel, Alfred M.; Richards, Dickinson W.; Dale, Sir Henry Hallett; Ellis, Lilliam N.
  - Albanese, Anthony A
  - Allen, Charles F H
  - American Academy of Arts & Sciences, 1968
    2 items, 1968 [Box 1] Circular letter informing Clarke that the Nominating Committee wished Clarke to be a nomiee for election to Councilor of the Class II, Section I -Biophysics and Biochemistry for the period May 1968-May 1972.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1963
    1 item, 1963 [Box 1]
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science--Abelson, Philip
    See also in reference to Science (Magazine)
  - American Chemical Society # 1, 1956-1966
    Sweting, Orville J.; Gaffin, Fisher; Philip, Brother Augustine; Noyes, W. Albert; Parham, William E.; Warren, R. M.; Elder, Albert L.; Tatum, E. L.
    3 files, c.300 items, 1956-1966. [Box 1] Clarke appointed to Garvan Medal Award Committee 1957. Letters re: nominees for the Garvan Medal 1959 and 1960.
    Certificate attesting to Clarke's membership of the ACS for 50 years, 1916-1966.
    Review of book by S.P. Datta & Ottoway "Aids to Biochemisty" by Clarke for the Journal of the American Chemical Society, Feb. 1961 [Box 1]
    See also: Awards and Certificates, in:
  - American Chemical Society # 2
    Parham, WIlliam E.; Tatum, E. L.; Warren, R. M.
  - American Chemical Society # 3
    Warren, R. M.; Du Vigneaud, Vincent; Dahl, Roland J.; Howard, John H.; Kemper, Arthur B.
  - American Chemical Society. Committee of Professional Training # 1, 1960-1961
    Patterson, Boyd Crumrine; Howard, John H.; Way, Harold E.; Philip, Brother Augustine; Jones, F. Taylor.
    2 files, c. 50 items, 1960-1961 [Box 1] Copy of the Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary School "Evaluators H andbook" for 1960. 2 Syllabi for chemical courses in 1961. Copy of report on the Dept. of Chemistry of Manhatten College, 1960. Correspondence to the from Clarke as official representative of the Middle States Association at Manhatten College, 1960.
  - American Chemical Society. Committee of Professional Training # 2
  - American Institute of Chemists
    Foy, George F.
  - American Music Center, Inc.
  - American Otological Society # 1, 1956-1962
    Meltzer, Philip E.; Fowler, Edmund P.
    9 files, 1956-1962. [Box 1] Records and correspondence to and from Clarke in his official capacity as consultant to Grants Committee of the American Otological Society. Grant proposals, minutes of Grant Committee meetings, administrative correspondence, etc.
  - American Otological Society # 2
    Kelemen, George; Meltzer Philip E.
  - American Otological Society # 3
    Meltzer, Philip E.; Baker, Walter C.; Fowler, Edmund P.
  - American Otological Society # 4
  - American Otological Society # 5
    Meltzer, Philip P.; Fowler, Edmund P.
  - American Otological Society # 6
  - American Otological Society # 7
    Lindsay, John R.
  - American Otological Society # 8
    Meltzer, Philip E.
  - American Otological Society # 9
  - American Philosophical Society # 1, 1943-1968
    Noonan, Julia A.; Hess, Mrs. Gertrude D.; Shryock, Richard Harrison, 1893-1972; Corner, George W.[ashington]; Richards, Marie A.
    3 files, c. 60 items, 1956-1962 [Box 1]
    Biographical sketch of Charles Edward Kenneth Mees. Correspondence re: new members of the A.P.S. and letters re: Clarke's membership 1943. Correspondence re: the writing of biographical memoirs for the A.P.S. Year Book. Correspondence re: teh A.P.S. Nominating Committee, 1958-1962.
  - American Philosophical Society # 2
    Menzel, Donald H.; Corner, George W.[ashington]; Noonan, Julia A.; Robbins, William Jacob; Chinard, Gilbert; Moe, Henry Allen (1894-); Nichols, Roy Franklin.
  - American Philosophical Society # 3
    Eisenhart, Luther P.; Carmichael, Leonard; Noonan, Julie A.; Chinard, Gilbert.
  - American Society of Biological Chemists # 1, 1942-1963
    Harte, Robert A.; Nachmansohn, David; Lawler, H. Claire.
    5 files, c. 50 items, 1942-1963 [Box 2]
    Presidential nomination forms - nomination of Helen Claire Lawler (sp.?: Lowther) to the Society 1962.
    ASBC Committee on Educational Affairs - Report on Conference on Training in Biochemistry held at the Rockefetter Institute, September 1960. Committee reports: 1942, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1961. Membership lists 1957-1963.
  - American Society of Biological Chemists # 2
    Stein, William H.; Lipmann, Fritz.
  - American Society of Biological Chemists # 3
  - American Society of Biological Chemists # 4
    Davis, Albert S., Jr.; Edsall, John T.; Handler, Philip.
  - American Society of Biological Chemists # 5
    Handler, Philip.
  - Amoros-Marin, Luis
  - Amino Acids and Proteins, 1945
    10 items, 1945 [Box 2]
    Referee report written by Clarke published in Science, June 1945. Letters re: Clarke to review an article for the Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1945.
  - Anchel, Marjorie, 1963
    Gross, Noel H.; [U. S.] National Institutes of Health
    10 items, 1963 [Box 2] Letters relating to the National Institutes of Health Career Award, 1963.
  - Anderson, Elder O N
  - Anderson, Rudolph J
  - Anker, Herbert S
  - Annual Reviews, Inc., 1957-1965
    Luck, J. Murray.
    Annual Review of Biochemistry 8 items, 1957-1965 [Box 2]
    Letter asking Clarke's permission to include Clarke's articles in the Journal.
    Subscription order and payment slips. Letters. re: Clarke's writing a prefactory chapter for issue of 1958.
  - Apgar, Virginia
    See also: Wu, Tai Te, in:
  - Aquinas Institute
  - Arnold, Edward, Ltd. (Publishers), 1911, 1926-1963
    Price, P. J.
    c. 20 items, 1911 & 1926-63 [Box 2]
    Letter re: publication of Clarke's book "Organic Analysis," 1911 and later arrangements for its revision.
  - Arnold, Richard T
    See also: Nobel Prize - A, in:
  - Asenjo, Conrado F
  - Atchley, Dana Winslow, 1892-
  - Atoms for Peace Awards
  - Auchincloss, Hugh
  - Awards and Certificates # 1 (A-H)
    American Academy of Arts and Sciences; American Chemical Society; American Institute of Chemists; American Philodosophical Society; American Society of Biological Chemists; Athenaeum; Children's Hospital, Boston; Clarke, Hans T., Associates; Great Britain. Embassy; Harvard Universary.
  - Awards and Certificates # 2 (I-U)
    Institute of Chemists of Great Britain and Ireland; Rochester Torch Club; Sigma Xi; University of London; University of Rochester; United States.
  - Axmann, Heidrum
  - Bachmann, Mrs. Marie K
  - Bachmann, Werner E
  - Bailey, J L
  - Baitsell, George A
  - Ball, John
  - Ball, Kent
  - Barnard School for Boys
    Zeeman, Roger D.
  - Bartlett, Paul D
  - Barton, Edwin M, P and S Club
  - Beatty, Clarissa Hager
  - Bergmann, Max (Obituary), 1945
    i item, 1945 {Box 2]
    Obituary written for Science, July 30, 1945.
  - Berry, Frank B
    See: Conant, James B
  - Berry, George Packer
  - Bieber, Theodore I
  - Biochemical Preparations # 1
    Coon, M. J.
  - Biochemical Preparations # 2
    Meister, Al.
  - Biochemical Preparations # 3
  - Biochemical Preparations # 4
    Carter, Herbert E.
  - Biochemical Society
  - Biochemistry
    Nevrath, Hans
  - Biochemistry - Columbia University, 1913-1957 & 1955
    1 items, 1955 [Box 2]
    College of Physicians & Surgeons: List of Ph.D.'s in Biochemistry granted from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, 1913-1957 and list of their activities in 1955.
  - Birnbaum, George
    See also: Journal of Experimental Medicine, in:
  - Bittinger, Charles
  - Blake, Eleanor M
  - Blakely, Wesley H
  - Bloch, Konrad
  - Blount, B K
  - Bond, V P
  - Bookplates
  - Borek, Ernest
  - Bowen, Catherine Drinker
  - Boyd, Mrs. Vallency
  - Bradley, O L
  - Bradley, Ruth
  - Bradley, Stanley E